Guide to the Vassily Aksyonov papers, 1980s-2004
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
Vassily Aksyonov papers
1980s-2004
C0062
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
8.0 linear feet (20 boxes)
This collection contains papers, manuscripts, and some correspondence, research material, interviews, and reviews, of acclaimed novelist and former George Mason University Robinson Professor Vassily Aksyonov.
Aksenov, Vasilii, 1932-2009
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Vassily Aksyonov in 2004.
Biographical Information
Born in 1932, Vassily Pavlovich Aksyonov was a prominent Russian novelist who spent much of his later career writing and teaching in the Washington, DC area. Aksyonov was born in the Russian city of Kazan and grew up under Stalin's rule. Askyonov's parents, although devoted communists, were accused of being Trotskyites and sent to gulags when he was still a child. Aksyonov was subsequently raised in an orphanage for "children of enemies of the state" before moving in with his aunt and uncle, who tried to keep the truth of his parents' disappearance a secret. He spent much of his youth listening to jazz and reading American novels, which would influence his work as much as the disenchantment and paranoia of life under Stalinism.
Though trained as a medical doctor, Vassily Aksyonov gave up his medical career in the 1960s to pursue a career as a novelist. His 1961 novel, A Ticket to the Stars, drew a great deal of praise from readers and helped launch his career. His writings quickly became controversial as they celebrated Western popular culture and criticized life under Stalin and his successors. During the 1960s he wrote several plays that were denounced by the state press for spreading "negativism," and after voicing public opposition to the Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia in 1968, no publisher would print his work for the next 12 years, during which he worked as a translator to support his family. By the 1970s, Aksyonov had become one of the most popular prose writers in Russia, but his popularity only exacerbated his low standing with the communist party, which disapproved of his criticism and revoked his citizenship in 1980, when he decided to emigrate to the United States. Aksyonov settled in Washington, DC, where he taught literature and continued to write until moving back to Russia in 2004.
During his stay in America, Aksyonov published several novels that he had kept hidden in drawers during the 1970s, including The Burn (1980) and The Island of Crimea (1983). His later works include In Search of Melancholy Baby (1987), Say Cheese (1989), Generations of Winter (1994), The Winter's Hero (1996), and The New Sweet Style (1999). Aksyonov taught at The Johns Hopkins University and Goucher University before coming to George Mason University, where he taught from 1988 to 2004, when he moved back to Russia to live out his remaining years. He died in 2009.
Scope and Content
This collection contains papers, manuscripts, and some correspondence, research material, interviews, and reviews, of acclaimed novelist and former George Mason University Robinson Professor Vassily Aksyonov. The collection includes handwritten and typed notes for novels, plays, articles, poems, and other writings in Russian and English. Writings include "The Caesaian Selection", "Kesarevo Svechenie", "Desyatiletie Kleveti", Noviy Sladostniy Stil'", "Ten Years of Slander", "Generations of Winter", "The Wiesbaden Journal", "The Yolk of the Egg", "Say Cheese", "Zheltok Yaitsa", "Blues with a Russian Accent", "In Search of Melancholy Baby", and "Pik Kommunizma". A small selection of audio visual material is comprised of two audio cassette tapes that include recordings of interviews with Aksyonov and three VHS tapes, one of which features his retirement at George Mason University.
Arrangement
Organized by subject.
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds other collection of papers from Robinson Professors.
Index Terms
Persons:
Aksenov, Vasilii, 1932-2009
Subjects:
Criticism.; Fiction.
Contents List
- Vassily Aksyonov papers, 1980s-2004
  - "Radio Journal of a Writer Aksyonov, The Caesaian Selection," Akyonov's handwritten manuscript in Russian, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Contains chapters I and III, pages 1-172. Each chapter is marked with personal notes. Manuscript has a few cartoons. Pages have a variation in page numbering. Riche Linge, personal correspondence to Lily Denis A, January 5, 2000. Newspaper article from Newsweek - The Case Against Legalization: The U.N's drug czar on supply and demand, November 1, 1999.
  - "Radio Journal of a Writer Aksyonov, The Caesaian Selection," Akyonov's handwritten manuscript in Russian, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Contains chapters IV and VI, pages 173-405. Page 57 has personal notes. Page 301 has a table of contents that lists six chapters of the novel. Contains a poem, August 1, 1999.
  - "Radio Journal of a Writer Aksyonov, The Caesaian Selection," Akyonov's handwritten manuscript in Russian, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Pages 406-670. Page 415 contains a poem without a title. Page 456 contains a personal poem. Other poems are on pages: 465, 467, 492, 493, 494, and 657.
  - "Radio Journal of a Writer Aksyonov, The Caesaian Selection," Akyonov's handwritten manuscript in Russian, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Pages 671-832. Page 775 marks chapter X.
  - "Voltaireans" (Missian Monuscript) Printed Material in Russian, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Novel "Vol'ter'yantsi i Vol'ter'yanki". File: Semiramada pages 1-215. Contains some personal notes.
  - "China" Printed Material in Russian, novel "Kesarevo Svechenie" (1 of 2), September 2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Pages have a variation in page numbering. The novel begins with page 3-165 or 301-449. Contains somebody else's personal notes. Pages 450-477 begin with part X and have an essay diary, "Vesna v kontse veka" with a series of poems.
  - "China" Printed Material in Russian, novel "Kesarevo Svechenie" (2 of 2), September 2000 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Contains a continuation of an essay diary. Pages have a variation in page numbering. pp 478- 643. Page 485 begins with part XI titled "Pegas Pikasso"; it also contains a label that has Aksyonov's fax (1-703-352-3330) to Kabanov ( 7-095-943-9792). The fax has a part "Pegas Pikasso" from "Kesarevo Svechenie". The novel is written in Fairfax, VA.
  - Novel "Kesarevo Svechenie" typed manuscript in Russian, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Dedicated to Ivan. Contains a table of contents. Pages have a variation in page numbering. pp 1-129. Page 80 contains Fax for M. F. [3.1]
  - Novel "Kesarevo Svechenie" (continued), typed manuscript in Russian, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    The novel is unfinished. pp 130-300 [3.2]
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie" novel, typed manuscript in Russian, September 2000 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Starting with page 51 a new count of pages begins. pp 1-118.
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie" novel, typed manuscript in Russian, September 2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Begins with part 5 "Gore, Gora, Goret'". pp 119-218.
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie" novel, typed manuscript in Russian, September 2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Begins with part 7 "Kukushkini ostrova". pp 219-298.
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie" novel, typed manuscript in Russian, September 2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Begins with a story titled "Baby Cassandra" pp 299-449.
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie" novel, typed manuscript in Russian, September 2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Begins with part 10 titled "Vesna v kontse veka" (Dnevnik Sochinitelya. A creator's diary). Contains a series of poems. pp250-574.
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie" novel, typed manuscript in Russian, September 2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Begins with part 14 titled "Ah, Artur Shopengauer!" (Script in two parts) pages 575-643. Pages have a variation in page numbering.
  - Raznie Teksti, various texts, 1943-1999 (Oversize 19)
    Contains a fax from Pan. Peonides to Vassily Aksyonov and another fax from Aksyonov to Peonides in English, May 30, 1999; A story "University as a Metaphor" in English, pp 1- 13, no date; "The Novelist in the University" in English, pp 1-15, no date; "A Trolley-Bus' Blues" in English, pp 1-25, December, 1998; A letter from Aksyonov to Daniel Menaker, Vice-President, in English, December 6, 1998; Fax from Aksyonov to Valeriy Kalashnikov in Russian, no date; Fax to Il'ya Medovoy, "Obshaya Gazeta" in Russian, no date; Fax from Znamya (Literary and socio-political journal) to Aksyonov in Russian, February 24, 1997; "Nostalgia or Schizophrenia?" (Fall recollections of the summer impressions) in English, pp 1-16,November, 1997; "President of an Old Tsardom" in English, (11569 Avondale Drive) Fairfax, VA, no date; "A Trolley-Bus' Blues" in English, no date, pp 1- 26; "Gikkie and BabyCassandra" in English, pp 1-14, April 1999; Documentation on Shalamov's criminal case, 1943; Articles from Soviet newspapers, Russian Daily: Novoe Russkoe Slovo, on Boris Balter in Russian, June 8, 1984; on Sakharov's forced psychiatrical treatment, June 11, 1984; on Aksyonov frustrating the Soviet authorities; and other articles.
  - Raznie Teksti, various texts, 1997-2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Information drawn from various web sites: Chronology on Catherine the Great from wysiwyg://zoffsitebottom.156/...; Biography on Catherine the Great, January, 2000; A series of photographs and articles on Voltaire in English; "Universitet Kak Metafora" hand written manuscript; GMU flyers "Clarence J. Robinson Professor of Russian Literature and Writing", April 15, 1997; A document from Pegasus Prize for Literature 1977-1997; Table Des Matieres in French; Fax from Aksyonov to Loshak, chief editor from weekly newspaper ?, in Russian, October 27, 1997; Fax from Zoya Boguslavskaya, "Nezavis Blagotvoritel'niy Fond". Launch Tour of Mario de Carvalho. Public Schedule, July, 10 1997; Letter from Michael Morgan (Pegasus Prize for Literature) in English, announcing that the Portuguese winner, July 29, 1997.
  - "Desyatiletie Kleveti." (Creator's Radio Diary. Radio Dnevnik pisatelya), typed manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Contains a table of contents and epigraph to the novel. pp1-139.
  - "Desyatiletie Kleveti." (Creator's Radio Diary. Radio Dnevnik pisatelya), typed manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Pages 140-308.
  - "Desyatiletie Kleveti." (Creator's Radio Diary. Radio Dnevnik pisatelya), typed manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Pages 309-537. Page 535 has epilogue.
  - "The Wiesbaden Journal", 1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    "Ah, Artur Shopengauer" Play and other documents. (Play in two acts), Aksyonov's handwritten manuscript in Russian, October 10, 1998; pages 1-96. A play has personal notes; Contains a short story "The Wiesbaden Journal" by Vassily Aksyonov in English, August (1864); An abrupt newsletter addressed to Aksyonov in Russian on the issue of Bill Clinton and Monica, October 29, 1998; An invitation letter to Aksyonov from the National Gallery of Canada; A flyer on "Writers on Exile and Migration" in English and French, August 7-November 1, 1998.
  - "Noviy Sladostniy Stil'" Aksyonov's handwritten manuscript, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Has a title "Iz rukopisi "Novogo Sladostnogo Stilya" (partially in English) and partially in Russian, December 1994, February 1996. Chernovik. Draft. Starts with page 1057-1182.
  - Aksyonov's handwritten manuscript of a play "Slava Gorelik, Istoriya Avantyurista" in Russian, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Aksyonv's personal documents and correspondence. "Avrora Gorelika" (drama in two acts); George Mason University papers and CV. Contains personal notes and a drawing on the front page, and a caricature. pp. 1-79. Contains monologue of the creator of Gorelik. Curriculum Vitae of Aksyonov in English; A letter from Aksyonov to Prof. Leo Hecht, Chairman of Russian Studies at GMU, in English, September 15, 1987; A document called Briefing Material in English, no date; A letter from Hecht to Aksyonov in English, July 27, 1988; Correspondence between Aksyonov and Ms. Carol Krider, November 15, 1987; The documents of Aksyonov's employment with GMU; Correspondence of Aksyonov with GMU faculty and staff.
  - "Generations of Winter" Treatments 1-5. 2nd Draft, typed manuscript in English., September 1998 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Treatment for program one. The Roaring Twenties (working title) two hours. Written in California. Pages have a variation in page numbering.
  - "Ten years of Slander", typed manuscript in Russian, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Pages 1-130. "Desyatiletie Kleveti" (radio-dnevnik pisatelya).
  - "Ten years of Slander", typed manuscript in Russian, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Pages 131-310.
  - "Ten years of Slander", typed manuscript in Russian, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Pages 311-504. Page 311 begins with "Buistvo Demokratii". Page 504 has a phone number of Iris Knell.
  - Various manuscripts. Raznie rukopisi., 1990-1999 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    [Separated into two folders] Contains a novel "Noviy Sladostniy Stil'" Partly typed and partly handwritten manuscript in English and Russian, 1996; Typed from pp 1-15. Handwritten from pp16-26. Contains personal notes, typed poems in Russian. One poem has a date, May 1, 1999; A personal notebook in English and Russian; Personal story in Russian, December, 1990, Moscow, Dom Kino; More handwritten poems in Russian; More personal notes; Correspondence from Popov to Aksyonov in Russian, handwritten, date signed August 11, 1997, date shown on the top left corner is August 11, 1998; Has a completion of some play in Russian and some in English. Zavershenie. Contains personal notes; A novel in Russian, hand written manuscript. Chapter I-IV.
  - Various Manuscripts and Correspondence., 1996-1999 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    "Noviy Sladostniy Stil" in English, hand written manuscript, pages 1-46, 1996; Personal fax from Aksyonov to Popov in Russian, hand written; Poem in Russian, handwritten with personal notes. Other poems are typed; A set of poems in Russian, handwritten, no date, "Dve Revo... Lotsiya" (handwriting is not clear); Hand written manuscript in English, pp 1-21. "Gikkie and Baby Cassandra."; An auto-portrait. Russian 327, 1999; A hand written novel in Russian that starts with the words Summer 1988. pages 1-33; Fax from Aksyonov to Vogue, Yurat Gurauskayte, in Russian, February 2, 1999; A handwritten Happy Birthday note to Sasha Kolt in English; A letter from Yvon Girard, Editions Gallimard, to Aksyonov, informing Aksyonov about Editions Gallimard reprinting his "Moskovskaya Saga", English, November 26, 1996, Paris; Aksyonov's response to Girard, December 8, 1996; Letter from Aksyonov to Peonides, handwritten in English, September 22, 1999; Letter from Aksyonov to Harold Evans, President of the Random House Publishing, in English, January 27, 1997; Another letter to Evans, November 22, 1996; Fax from Evgeniy Popov to Aksyonov, in Russian, handwritten, November 13, 1997; Letter from Aksyonov to Loshak in Russian, March 31, 1998; Letter from Popov to Aksyonov in Russian, September 11, 1997; Letter from Per Delgard in Russian, October 1, 1997; Letter from Aksyonov to Mary A. Frisque in English, April 26, 1997; Letter from Mary to Aksyonov in English, April 22, 1997; A novel "Checking the Pulse", handwritten manuscript in English; Fax from Andrey Kabannikov in Russian, March 28, 1999. Skeptical comments on the US involvement in the Balkans. pages 1-3; Fax from Skobelev to Aksyonov in Russian, September 8, 1998, Samara; Letter from Goran Rosenberg, Moderna Tider, to Aksyonov in English, April 6, 1998. Includes a translation of Aksyonov's novel, USSR Revisited and Aksyonov's thank you note to Goran, April 8, 1998.
  - Various manuscripts, 1994-1999 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Novel "Noviy Sladostniy Stil."; Typed poems in Russian, with a few personal notes, February 17, 1998; Story "Logovo L'va", handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 1-8; Letter from Popov to Aksyonov, March 10, 1999, Moscow. Has a press cutting with a caricature; Fax from Peonides to Maya Aksyonova, September 21, 1999; Handwritten manuscript of a untitled novel in English, begins with page 983-1182, December 1994, February 1996. Drafts. Washington, Paris, Moscow, Samara, Tel-a-Viv, Gotland.
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie". Novel, typed manuscript in Russian, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Contains personal list of correction notes. pages 1-175. Page numbers have double counting.
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie". Novel, typed manuscript in Russian, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Pages 176-384. Page numbers have double counting.
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie". Novel, typed manuscript in Russian, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Pages 385-643. Page 385 ends the first smena (konets pervoy smeni). The end, September, 2000, Fairfax.
  - Materials in English, 1965-undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Various correspondence. A few short stories in English; Aksyonov's "Victory": A Post-Analysis. Alexander Zholkovsky, typed in English, 1965; The Russian Acoustic. Songs to Seven Strings by Gerald Stanton Smith, hand written in English, pages 1-15; "A Soviet Odyssey". Typed manuscript in English, pages 1-13, no date; Two copies of "Love Story Kremlin Style" typed in English, 1-5, no date; Personal note typed in English about Aksyonov's theater-going habits; "Leningrad's Thrillers", typed short story in English, pages 1-9; "The Inspector General Goes to Topeka" (An attempt to envision an upcoming event) short story typed in English, pages 1-8 "Roundtable: the Lexicon of Soviet Propaganda: Its connotative Content." James P. Scanlan pp 1-4, typed; "Orgy of Evolution". Handwritten manuscript in English, pages 1-5; "The Leningrad's Thrillers". Typed in English with personal corrections, pages 1-4.
  - Materials in English, 1984-1992 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    "Guests from the Future" by Josephine Woll, review article in English, 1984; "Oda Dlya Rudi", typed in Russian, April 23, 1986; "A Soviet Odyssey", typed in English, late spring 1986, California; "Inspector General Goes to Topeka", pp1-8, typed in English; Personal story about Aksyonov's ideal American reader, typed in English, pages 1-13; Interview with Aksenov by Bella Ezerskaya in English, translated by Nancy Condee and Vladimir Padunov, pages 1-16; Letter to Raymond Whitley in English, October 7, 1986; "The Inspector General Goes to Topeca" typed in English with personal corrections; "From the Barracks to the Market" typed in English, pages 1-5; "Participantes in the Morelia Symposium: Approaching the Year 2000." Letter of Recommendation to Mr. Christian Nagle, typed in English, January 8, 1992; Novels "Ozhog" and "Ostrov Krym" November 2, 1985. Paper presented at the Third World Congress for Soviet and East European Studies. Typed in English, pages 1-14; "H2O and Polluting Letters", handwritten and typed in English; "Basketball, God, and the Ringo Kid: Philistinism and the Ideal in Aksenov's Short Stories." Typed in English, pages 1-20; A typed story in English with missing pages 1-7; "The Sound of Champs D'Elesee", typed in English with personal corrections, pages 1-6; Letter from Jane Uscilka, editorial assistant, to Aksyonov, in English, August 13, 1992; Letter from Eileen Godlis, Jankow and Nesbit Associates, to Aksyonov, in English June 22 1992; Four copies of Aksyonov's CV in English till 1987; Fax to Betty Ferber de Aridjis in English, May 13, 1992; "The Alchemic Lemon" typed in English with personal corrections, pages 1-16; "Gratitude to Our Former Rulers" typed in English; "From the Barracks to the Market" typed in English, pages 1-9; "In Avant-Garde with No Rear" typed in English, pages 1-6; "Without False Sound" typed in English; "And Again: Does Art Belong to Masses?" typed in English; "The Sound of Chmps D'Elesee", typed in English, pp 1-11; "Zhiteli I Bezhentsi" typed in Russian, pp1-11, September 1989; Letter to Leo Hecht from Anna Lawton, George Mason University, April 6, 1990; Aksyonov's personal correspondence in English.
  - Drafts and Manuscripts, 1990-2000 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    "A Winged Endangered Species" handwritten manuscript in English, pages 1-42; "Orgy of Evolution" typed manuscript in English, pages 1-5, USA Today; "Rebels Without (and with) a cause." "Beatniks and Bolsheviks." A printed article from the New Republic in English, pp28-32. Page 31 is missing; "Leningrad Thriller" Soviet Literary Criticism Continues Down a Bizarre Path, With Profound Implications, a printed article from American Politics, pages 5-7. Contains attached typed manuscript of "Leningrad Thriller" in English, pages 1-9; "The Tongue-Tied Glasnost" a typed manuscript in English, contains personal notes. Attached is a printed article by Aksyonov from Harper's Magazine, April, ?. "Through the Glasnost, Darkly. A cool reaction to Gorbachev's Thaw"; "Lungs and Gills", typed manuscript in English; Aksyonov's Curriculum Vitae in English to Spiros Avgenikos, September 20, 1999, pages 1-5; "Liberal -Eto Zvuchit Yasno" (Chitaya Leontovicha), typed manuscript in Russian. Contains a fax to Kabanov, October 30, 2000 and a fax to Aksyonov from Triumph Logovaz, October 24, 2000; Untitled story typed in Russian. First part is titled "Vezdekhod", pages 1-25; A set of poems typed in Russian; "The Novelist in the University", typed manuscript in English, pages 1-15; A letter from Richard C. Rowson to Aksyonov in English, September 27, 1993; Email from Aksyonov to Limanov in Russian, April 13, 1994; Article by Aksyonov from the New Republic, "A Countercoup of the Spirit. Live Souls" September 16 & 23, 1991; The title is personally scratched out and renamed into "Three Days that Shook the World" in English; "A Winged Endangered Species" typed manuscript in English, March 23, 1992, pages 1-27. Attached is a typed version of "A Winged Endangered Species" for Partisan Review, pages 180-188; "After a Decade in Exile, Back to the USSR. Not Quite a Sentimental Journey." Typed story in English, pages 1-11; Attached is a published "Not Quite a Sentimental Journey" for the New Republic, April 16, 1990, pages 21-25; The Woodrow Wilson Center Memorandum, September 15, 1993 in English; "Moscow Fever" typed manuscript in English, pages 1-86, March 1993; Untitled story, handwritten manuscript, pages 1-6; List of Vassily Aksyonov's Works Since 1975 (Information for a literary agency) in English; "The Metropole's Affair", typed in English story, pages 1-4; "The Human Factor", typed in English story, pages 1-8.
  - Drafts and Manuscripts, 1992-1995 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    "Gratitude to Wachdogs" typed manuscript in English, pages 1-6; "Three Days that Shook the Idols" hand written manuscript in English, pages 1-9; "The Literary Impact of the American and French Revolutions", Participants: Aksyonov and Susan Sontag, August 14, 1992, pages 1-54; "Leningrad's Thrillers" typed manuscript in English, pages 1-9; "The Lip-Sided Success" typed manuscript in English, pages 1-12; Untitled story, hand written manuscript in English; "The 1992 Neustadt International Prize for Literature Jurors and Candidates" by William. Riggan, pages 140-1 - 146-2; A note in English to Lev Ponomarev; A letter from the Golden Key, February 28, 1992; "Music Seminar" hand written manuscript in English with personal notes; "Moscow Theater of Absurd" hand written manuscript in English; A piece that is a continuation of some story, hand written manuscript in English; A hand written manuscript on the Soviet censorship, in English, pages 1-26; "Of my youth, the Golden Stalinist Fifties", typed manuscript in English; Several copies of "the Wiesbaden Journal" in English, Common Knowledge, winter 1995, V4, N3.
  - Pieces of Prose in Russian, 1965-1980 (Box 7, Folder 2)